Guide to the New-York Historical Society Publication Editorial Records 1939-2000, 2009 NYHS-RG 17
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society publication editorial records
1939-2000, 2009
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 17
36.5 Linear feet in 44 document boxes and 19 boxes of note cards
The New-York Historical Society publication editorial records include material related to publications produced by N-YHS from the 1940s to the early 1990s, with some later documents. Much of the record group includes the files of N-YHS's Editorial Department, which existed from about 1942 to 1980, and relates to the editorial work for articles proposed and written for the organization's journal, the Quarterly. The files also include editorial records for some of the books published by N-YHS, especially George C. Groce and David H. Wallace's Dictionary of Artists in America (1957), for which there is extensive correspondence and research notes. The record group also includes the papers presented at a series of six conferences on historical themes sponsored by N-YHS and organized by historian William Pencak from 1983 to 1988, along with the editorial files for the four volumes co-edited by Pencak based on the conference proceedings. Other principal correspondents include editors Charles E. Baker and Kathleen Luhrs, designer Klaus Gemming, members of N-YHS's Publications Committee, and authors William Sawitzky, Susan Clay Sawitzky, Mary Bartlett Cowdrey, Paul H. Downing, Irwin Cortelyou, Rita Gottesman, and others.
Accruals Note
No further accruals are expected for this record group.
Arrangement Note
The record group is organized in three series:
I. Publications, 1940s-1960s
II. Publications, 1960s-1980
III. Publications, 1980s-2000
Biographical/Historical Note
From its earliest years, the New-York Historical Society was actively engaged in publishing materials ranging from pamphlets of individual addresses on historical topics to collections of edited historical documents to monographic studies. In his 1954 history of N-YHS, R.W.G. Vail counted about 600 such publications and provided an overview of them. Among the several publishing initiatives was the New-York Historical Society Quarterly Bulletin. Begun in 1917, the Bulletin published feature articles, notes on N-YHS's activities, transcripts of historical documents in the collection, and other matter. Yet despite the extensive range of publishing activities, until the mid-twentieth century there was no staff dedicated to editorial activities. Until 1938, the Librarian and Assistant Librarian performed editorial tasks along with their other responsibilities.
This began to change in 1938 with the designation of Assistant Librarian Dorothy C. Barck as Editor and Head of Research. Still, though, Barck worked within N-YHS's library and held responsibilities well beyond editing the institution's publications; indeed, she was named Librarian in 1942. But N-YHS's drive in the late 1930s and early 1940s to expand its programs and professional operations led in 1943 to the hiring of Charles E. Baker as N-YHS's first full-time editor and the establishment of an Editorial Department reporting to the Director. Baker remained Editor until 1963.
There were at least two notable accomplishments during Baker's tenure that are well-represented in this record group's documents: the expansion and increased scholarly content of the Quarterly Bulletin (called the Quarterly from 1946) and the production of George C. Groce and David H. Wallace's Dictionary of Artists in America (DAA). The DAA was an initiative begun in the early 1940s to expand on art historian George Groce's 1940 survey of early American artists. Groce, living in Washington, DC, worked with Baker on the DAA for well over a decade before it was published in 1957. Along the way, N-YHS hired David H. Wallace as an assistant editor in 1952, with principal responsibility for seeing the DAA to a conclusion. Wallace completed the task just before leaving N-YHS in 1956, earning co-authorship credit with Groce for the achievement.
During his twenty years as Editor at N-YHS, Baker oversaw the production of several books in addition to the DAA and worked with many authors, including William Sawitzky and his wife Susan Clay Sawitzky, Rita Gottesman, Theodore Bolton, Paul H. Downing, Lawrence H. Leder, and others. After Baker's departure from N-YHS, the editorship was filled by a series of short-term appointments, including by Ann E. Cooper and Jane (Mrs. Wendell) Garrett, until 1967 when Kathleen A. Luhrs became Editor, a position she held until 1976. The mid-1960s were another important period for the Quarterly as a redesign of the journal by Klaus Gemming was well-received.
Elaine Andrews took over as Editor in 1977, but she was the last to hold that position at N-YHS. Financial difficulties resulted in the decision to no longer publish the Quarterly after its first number of 1980 and the Editorial Department was disbanded. Through the end of the twentieth century, N-YHS still continued to produce publications, but no longer on a regular basis with a full-time dedicated staff. An important example of these later publications, represented in this record group, are the four volumes published from 1988-1991 of papers based on conferences held at N-YHS from 1983 to 1988. The six conferences were organized for N-YHS by William Pencak, a professor of history at Pennsylvania State University. Organized around particular themes, the conference titles were: New Approaches to the History of Colonial and Revolutionary New York (1983); New York and the Rise of American Capitalism (1984); Law in America (1985); Immigration to New York (1986); New York in the Age of the Constitution (1987); and Labor in New York (1988). Although the original intent was to publish all or most of the papers presented at the conferences, financial constraints resulted in only the first four conferences appearing in print. Pencak co-edited the volumes with the logistical arrangements handled by Marilyn McShane, a freelancer hired in November 1987 by N-YHS to guide the delayed volumes to completion.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives).
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society publication editorial records include the files of the Editorial Department from its early days in the 1940s under Charles E. Baker to the close of the Department in 1980. There are also files from the 1980s, primarily in connection with the series of six conferences sponsored by N-YHS from 1983 to 1988 and the resulting volumes published from 1988 to 1991. The record group includes correspondence with authors in relation to the editing process; internal N-YHS notes assessing manuscripts for publication; manuscript submissions and edited versions of the manuscripts; and documents related to arrangements for printing and publicity. The files related to the conferences of the 1980s include all the papers originally presented at those sessions. Much of the record group concerns articles proposed and written for the Quarterly. Published books are also the subject of the record group, especially the production of the Dictionary of Artists in America. Efforts by William Sawitzky and, after his death, his wife Susan Clay Sawitzky to write a series of books on American artists in the 1940s-1950s are well-documented. The files also include various administrative matters such as arranging for photograph reproduction permissions, printing, publicity, book reviews, and the like.
Proofs (printed matter); Correspondence.; Learned institutions and societies -- Publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Museums -- Publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Editors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Libraries -- Publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historians -- Correspondence.; Editing; Art historians -- Correspondence; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Congresses and conventions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Wallace, David H. -- Correspondence; Groce, George Cuthbert, 1899-1962 -- Correspondence; Baker, Charles E. (Charles Edwin), 1902- -- Correspondence; Gottesman, Rita Susswein, 1906-1963 -- Correspondence; Sawitzky, Susan Clay, 1897-1981 -- Correspondence; Cowdrey, Mary Bartlett, 1910-1974 -- Correspondence; Bolton, Theodore, 1889-1973 -- Correspondence; Sawitzky, William, 1879 or 1880-1947 -- Correspondence; New-York Historical Society. Editorial Department; Dickson, Harold E., 1900- -- Correspondence; Yale University Press -- Correspondence; New-York Historical Society -- Archives; New-York Historical Society -- Publishing
- Series I. Publications (1940s-1960s)., 1939-1982, 2009; 24.42 Linear feet
  Arrangement Note
  The series is organized in three subseries:
  I.A. General Correspondence
  I.B. Dictionary of Artists in America Records
  I.C. David H. Wallace Papers
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series includes the Editorial Department files concerning certain publications of the 1940s and into the early 1960s. George C. Groce and David H. Wallace's Dictionary of Artists in America, published in 1957, is the best documented publication in the series. There is extensive correspondence between N-YHS editors Charles E. Baker and David Wallace and Groce, as well as with Yale University Press concerning production and royalty payments. The original cards used to record research notes and sources for the DAA entries are in the series. And the series also holds much correspondence and notes concerning information about artists provided after the DAA's publication in anticipation that a supplement to the DAA might be prepared. The series also includes a 2015 donation of documents from David Wallace that includes extracts from his diaries and other documents dating from his years working at N-YHS and with Groce on the DAA.
  In addition to the DAA, the series includes correspondence related to articles for the Quarterly and various book-length works. Unfinished and unpublished projects are represented in the series as well as published works. Although much of the general correspondence files concern administrative matters, such as acquiring image reproduction permissions, many files touch on more substantive matters, such as the editorial and management decisions regarding whether or not to publish a piece and the sometimes fraught relationship between editor and author. William Sawitzky, Susan Clay Sawitzky, Paul Downing, Mary Bartlett Cowdrey, and Theodore Bolton are among the several correspondents represented in the general correspondence of the series.
  - Subseries I.A. General Correspondence, 1939-1982; 4.17 Linear feet
    The General Correspondence subseries is arranged alphabetically, following the order and labels of the original files. For the most part, the alphabetical order is based on correspondent name (which can be either an individual or an institutional affiliation), though some documents were foldered by a publication title or other topic.
    The General Correspondence subseries includes the files maintained principally during the tenure of N-YHS publications editor Charles E. Baker, from 1943 to 1963. Some of Baker's files appear to have been maintained for a time after his departure so the date range of the correspondence extends into the mid-1960s and, in the case of a file of copyright registrations, to the early 1980s. The correspondence concerns the editorial process for articles and book reviews for the Quarterly, as well as various book-length works. The material relates to works that were either published, unfinished and unpublished, or proposed but declined from the 1940s through the mid-1960s.
    Many of the files primarily include only administrative matters related to the editorial process, such as transmittal letters, photograph reproduction requests and permissions, arrangements for printing, requests for book reviewers, mailings of copies of the published work, and other such matters. Nevertheless, more substantive content can be found in several files; these include Baker's recommendations to the N-YHS Publications Committee regarding a proposed publication and the Committee's response and editorial comments to the author. Only a few files have manuscript drafts of the work and these are noted in the container list. A few files hold photographs and negatives; these are also noted in the container list.
    Among the more substantive topical files are those concerning Susan Clay Sawitzky's efforts through the late 1940s and into the early 1960s to continue the late William Sawitzky's publications on American artists; the unsuccessful Rockefeller Foundation-funded attempt to publish a book by Paul Downing on historic carriages; differences of historical interpretation with Eugene F. Kramer in connection with his proposed Quarterly article on the Harry Croswell case of 1802; and publication of Harold Edward Dickson's John Wesley Jarvis, American Painter. Among the many other correspondents with substantive content are Theodore Bolton, Irwin Cortelyou, Rita and Callman Gottesman, Fenwick Beekman, Mary Bartlett Cowdrey, Stuyvesant Fish, Lawrence H. Leder, Arthur Merritt, J.E. Strickland, Leonidas Westervelt, and George Zabriskie.
    This subseries does not include the principal editorial records for the Dictionary of Artists in America (see subseries I.B for those). However, this subseries does include a set of folders dating from after the DAA's publication that refer to corrections, updates and other matter related to a possible supplement. References to the DAA are also made at points in other correspondence in this subseries and these are identified in the container list notes.
    - A. General (2 folders), 1946-1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-2)
      Principal correspondents include William Akin, Albany Institute of History & Art, William M. Armstrong, J. Earl Arrington. Includes carbon copy of the Editorial Department Report at May 20, 1947.
    - Accomplice for Treason, 1952-1955 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
      Principal subject concerns arrangements for publication with Evans Printing Company and others.
    - Ames Book & Ames Supplement, 1950-1960 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
      Concerns the book Ezra Ames of Albany, a related exhibition at the Albany Institute of History & Art, and a published supplement to the Ames book. Principal correspondents: Irwin (Mrs. George B.) Cortelyou, Robert Wheeler (Albany Institute), Theodore Bolton. See also the folder below: Bolton, Theodore.
    - Arts & Crafts in New York (3 folders), 1947-1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5-7)
      Primarily concerns Rita Gottesman's Arts & Crafts in New York, 1777-1799 and the posthumously published Arts & Crafts in New York, 1800-1804, but also includes documents related to other writings and proposals of Gottesman. Principal correspondents include Rita Gottesman and Callman Gottesman.
    - B. General (2 folders), 1948-1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8-9)
      Prncipal correspondents include Helena Baer, Alexander S. Balinky, James F. Beard, Martin J. Becker, Whitfield J. Bell, Jr., George A. Billias, Walter H. Blumenthal, Metchie J.E. Budka.
    - Beekman, Fenwick (2 folders), 1946-1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10-11)
      Concerns Philip White's The Beekmans of New York in Politics and Commerce and articles and other writings by Fenwick Beekman. Includes research notes compiled for Beekman with biographical information on physicians who were N-YHS members.
    - Benson, Egbert, 1959 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes Phyllis Ross's manuscript essay "The Early Life of Egbert Benson." Ross was a graduate student at Columbia University and used N-YHS resources in researching the paper.
    - Bolton, Theodore (2 folders), 1939, 1947-1959, 1965 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2-3)
      Primarily concerns Bolton and Cortelyou's Ezra Ames of Albany and also other writings and review work done by Bolton. Includes some correspondence and references to George Groce and William Savitzky (1939). See also the folder above: Ames Book & Ames Supplement.
    - Budget & Bills, 1951-1966 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
      Includes informal yearly budget estimates and some printing bills for, primarily, the Annual Report and the Quarterly.
    - Bulletin / Quarterly (14 folders), 1943-1951 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-14)
      Includes correspondence primarily arranging for book reviews (obtaining reviewers and review copies, transmittals of drafts and comments, exchanges with the N-YHS Publications Committee members). Most are carbon copies of outgoing letters, though there are many incoming letters as well. Principal correspondents (i.e., those with more than basic exchanges) include Stuyvesant Fish, Lucy Stewart, Kiliaen Van Rensselaer, Charles Larned Robinson, John Perry Pritchett, Frank Weitenkamp, Harry C.W. Melick, Victor Hugo Paltsis, Alvin F. Harlow, George Zabriskie, Louis Wills (includes compliments of various correspondents to Wills for his 1947 article), Lockwood Barr, Kenneth Scott, D.G. Brinton Thompson, Roger L. Williams, Theodore Sizer, Thomas A. Larremore, Samuel White Patterson, Mary Bartlett Cowdrey, Robert Ernst, Paul H. Downing, J. Earl Arrington, Mrs. W.E. Smith, Leroy E. Kimball. There is one letter each from Eleanor Roosevelt (1945) and Irving Berlin (1948).
    - C. General (2 folders), 1948-1965 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5-6)
      Principal correspondents include Frances S. Childs, Mary E. Cunningham, Alexander B. Callow, Jr., Vincent P. Carosso, Roger Champagne, Annie R. (Mrs. Francis J.H.) Coffin, Thomas J. Condon, Irwin (Mrs. George B.) Cortelyou.
    - Case, Lockwood & Brainard (Printers), 1951-1952 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cooper, J., 1945, 1951-1954 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
      Concerns a Quarterly article and photograph(s) related to the artist, J. Cooper. Principal correspondents include George C. Groce, Mary (Mitzie) Bartlett Cowdrey, and various museums and galleries.
    - Copyright (2 folders), 1939-1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Cowdrey, Mary (Mitzie) Bartlett (4 folders), 1946-1956 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11-14)
      Concerns Cowdrey's American Academy of Fine Arts and American Art-Union, 1816–1852 and other writings, as well as other matters Cowdrey comments on. George Groce and the Dictionary of American Artists are referred to.
    - D. General, 1950-1965 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
      Principal correspondents include Joseph Downs, Curtis Carroll Davis.
    - Dana, Nathalie, 1962, 1964-1965 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
      Concerns Dana's Quarterly article "Lenox Hill in the 1800s" and her proposed longer work Flight from the Rectory, and other writings. Other correspondents include agent Virginia Rice and Jarvis Cromwell.
    - Dictionary of Artists in America (4 folders), 1956-1965 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3-6)
      Includes comments, inquiries, information on additional artists, corrections, and other matter from readers of the DAA. See also series II.B for the continuation of this correspondence in the late 1960s and after. See also subseries I.B, box 62 labeled "Note Cards. Some for Included Entries and Some for Excluded Entries. Abbott - Zieber" for related notes from circa 1956-1961.
    - Downing, Paul H. (4 folders), 1946-1962 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7-10)
      Primarily concerns Downing's attempt, which was not completed, to write a history of American carriages to 1800. Also includes documents concerning an earlier article written by Downing. Other correspondents include Dana Creel, Kenneth Chorley, Irving S. Olds, John E. Parsons, George R. Clay
    - E. General, 1949-1965 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
      Principal correspondents include David M. Ellis, Robert Ernst, John C. Ewers.
    - Edwards Brothers, Inc. (Lithoprinters), 1949-1961 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
    - Exhibition Catalogues, 1956, 1961 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
      Includes a few notes concerning price quotes and estimates for printing from Grady Press.
    - F. General, 1950-1966 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
      Principal correspondents include Paul Fatout, William N. Fenton, Kent Forster, Alfred Frankenstein, Warren G. French, Frick Art Reference Library.
    - Fish, Stuyvesant, 1944-1950 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
      Concerns Fish's opinions on various publications and his related book reviews and proposed reviews.
    - Furman, Gabriel, 1945 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
      Includes Charles Baker's notes and proposal to publish Furman's circa 1845 manuscript of "The Customs, Amusements, Style of Living, and Manners of the People of the United States...."
    - G. General, 1948-1965 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
      Principal correspondents include Helen P. Geng, Don R. Gerlach, Laurence B. Goodrich (in connection with William and Susan Clay Sawitzky's work on Ralph Earl), George C. Groce (1956-58, concerning the Dictionary of Artists in America).
    - George Grady Press, 1941-1962 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    - H. General (3 folders), 1947-1965 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6-8)
      Principal correspondents include Loyd Haberly, Hermann Hagedorn, Milton W. Hamilton, Paul M. Hamlin, William Hartman, (Rear Admiral) John D. Hayes, Leo Hershkowitz, Codman Hislop, Harry P. Havell, Elliot Baldwin Hunt, Beatrice Hyslop.
    - Harbor Press, Inc., 1962-1965 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
    - History Written with Pick and Shovel, 1950, 1954-1955 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
      Concerns reviews and other publicity for the 1950 book, and printing costs and publicity for the 1955 reprint.
    - I. General, 1953, 1958-1959, 1965 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
    - J. General, 1949-1964 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
      Principal correspondents include Herbert A. Johnson, William R. Johnson, Jacob Judd (includes Judd's unpublished manuscript article "A Tale of Two Cities: Brooklyn and New York, 1834-1855").
    - John Wesley Jarvis, American Painter (3 folders), 1947-1951, 1954 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2-4)
      Concerns Harold Edward Dickson's book on Jarvis.
    - K. General, 1953-1966 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
      Principal correspondents include Alice P. Kenney, Herbert Kriedman.
    - Knickerbocker Birthday, 1954-1955 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
      Concerns post-publication matters related to R.W.G. Vail's history of N-YHS, including requests for review copies and sales offers. There is also an informal list of printing costs.
    - Kramer Article, 1962-1964 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
      Concerns Eugene F. Kramer's unpublished article "The Harry Croswell Case: A Milestone in the Freedom of the Press." Includes a version with N-YHS's proposed edits.
    - L. General (3 folders), 1948-1966 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8-10)
      Principal correspondents include Vincent Peter Lannie, L. Jesse Lemisch, Ira M. Leonard, Edwin R. Lewinson, W. David Lewis, Clifford L. Long, Roy Lubove, Paul V. Lutz, Lila Parish Lyman.
    - Leder, Lawrence H. (2 folders), 1952-1955 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11-12)
      Concerns various writings of Leder. Includes a manuscript of his "The Missing New York Assembly Journal of April 1692."
    - M. General (2 folders), 1948-1966 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-2)